Right so this has to be true if v star is
truly a fixed point right something they star
is truly a fixed point then this will be 0
so there should be something greater than
zero right so because of the fact of this
being a norm there is no case of less than
zero so this is finest all of this is the
thing so now what we will do is we will use
our friend the triangle inequality again like
I say it is very simple proof right all we
are doing is just using the triangle inequality
again and again I souse a triangle in you
call it again so what we get so
what do we know we know that V n is Cauchy
so we know that V n is Cauchy.
So this sequence is going to this thing right
V star minus V n minus 1 is going to go to
zero I mean that is my definition of Cauchy
sequence V star minus V n minus 1 will go
to 0 likewise v n minus v star will also go
to zero by virtue of the fact that v n is
Cauchy that is a definition we had earlier
it so that is going to converge right so it
will go to 0 no v star is a convergent point
right so we know that v star because of the
being Barack you know that v star exists in
u right so that is the thing we had right
limit as n tends to infinity v n will go to
v star that is what we mean by saying it is
convergent weight limit as n tends to infinity
v nis going to v star.
So limit as n tends to infinity v star minus
v n will go to 0 limit as n tends to infinity
that is the crucial point here right it would
not be doing this forever and if the difference
is going to be something small when he goes
far away that means is not convergent that
is the assumption we have made see what I
am trying to prove is that
what I am trying to prove is that.
T V star equal to V star is a fixed point
that V star is a fixed point of T is what
I am trying to prove right the fact that v
n is Cauchy right when she tells me that if
I applied T or infinitely often enough I will
anyway converge to V star when we reach V
star . What I am trying to show is once is
v star you do not go anywhere you just stop
there under T that make sense so the sequence
I am generating V VN +1 VN + 2 and so on so
forth I am showing that it is Cauchy right
so that means if I applied t infinitely often
enough I will eventually reach infinitely
often infinite should be enough so if I apply
the infinitely often I will reach v star .
So that process is that what we are trying
to say is okay v star is actually a fixed
point once you reach me star you are going
nowhere take a little bit n tends to infinity
for we want one what would you have gotten
like in n equal to 1 and then m equal to 1
tending to infinity take a little bit yeah
what would have got it just becomes zero okay
and then you show that it is the successive
differences become 0 that is the v n plus
1 is can be written as Tv n minus v n will
be less than equal to 0 yeah.
So essentially you show that asset tends to
infinity it will become 0 you become it will
become 0 but you have to show that we v star
reaches v star to stop that that is all we
are showing here when it reaches v star it
would not go anywhere beyond v star that is
it right so we are just showing that it will
stop at v star that is basically what we are
trying to show here and since this is trivial
in fact we can actually show it that way also
as limit n tends to infinity okay now the
uniqueness
from the contraction property.
So U star and in V star or two different fixed
point 4 from the contraction property we have
TU star minus TV star should be less than
or equal to lambda times u star minus V star
norm of U star - v star but since they are
six points the right hand left hand side is
also U star - V star so I'm asking Q for U
star minus V star should be less than or equal
to lambda times U star minus v star for lambda
non 0 lambda that is satisfied only for only
if V star equal to u star e start to stop
well sorry if lambda is not 1 then it satisfied
for yeah so even if lambda is zero it has
to be that u star equal to v star okay.
This does not matter anyway just using the
contraction property just this is sufficient
to show that u star has to be equal to v star
rights as long as lambda is not one and anyway
we have excluded lambda 1 here right so as
long as lambda is not equal to 1 this implies
that.
Great so what we have done so far is shown
the at the benefits point theorem is correct
that we need to show that L pi is a contraction
so if you so L pi is a contraction you get
everything else for free right so we need
to show a a is a contraction so let us do
that and I will stop after that ah I do not
people stop me what okay when I do v minus
U V minus okay so far it just algebra okay
so now what I am going to say is well I do
not care what j I am considering the notation
so of U and V are vectors but US and Vs are
scalars but all the contraction mapping results
are four vector norms it so mean all the contraction
mapping is so far vector norms here.
So do element wise do they correspond to that
I mean the maximum of that particular vector
has to be lesser than the maximum of another
vector but each element wise they need not
be lesser element wise they need not be lesser
no that is I not needed yes only the max noun
ways yeah the max of this should be less than
that expression is again for a scalar expression
again for a scalar expression whatever I am
writing so far is a scalar I will come to
the vector form of this case so far I am writing
scalar now so the tricky thing you know I
am going to say so I am summing over all j
right so I am going to look at this expression.
So what I am going to serve is this expression
right will always be bounded by v minus U
like the max norm alright so this is a pretty
loose bond right so I am taking each element
here I am looking at this that each element
of this will be bounded at most by the maximum
right so it cannot be any greater than the
max norm difference therefore I will say that
this expression is lesser than or equal to
? times the max norm into that right so that
anyway goes to zero so this is essentially
equal to okay.
So at every point this will satisfy that this
is one way so go the other way me let into
the other way easily enough right you will
end up with the same thing norm of V minus
U the same of Norm of U minus V so we will
end up with the same expression right so essentially
I can say that so I am assuming that you guys
will finish the other way around okay.
So what is otherwise is when L pi V of s is
less than L pi V of s okay so greater than
less than so I am just assuming you guys will
do that right putting these things together
gives us what right so what can infer from
this point place it is being drawn closer
right by gamma so the max difference should
also have come down point where is being drawn
closer even if the max difference is at different
points right it should have shrunk all right
so essentially that so this essentially means
that implies that L pi is a contraction.
So next thing to do is to start the same thing
for the optimality equation right so we will
go here in the next class and then I have
to also talk about so assuming that at every
point at every point the functions are being
drawn closer so I am saying that see L pi
VS minus L pi us is closer right then the
max difference that you had in V minus U right
and this holds for all state S right and that
the otherwise the right-hand side is infinity
norm left-hand side is just absolute value
so we also have to show algorithms for solving
this right and so we will do all of that in
the next class possibly it might spill over
into the subsequent class as well.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved